{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "One side’s plans in this battle were almost revealed by a premature attack from Adam Stephen. The losing side of this battle had earlier been weakened by the departure of Carl von Donop’s men. The password “victory or death” was used in this battle, in which Johann Rall was mortally wounded. A famous painting by Emanuel Leutze [loyt-zah] depicts how the winning side in this battle crossed the Delaware River on Christmas Eve. For ten points, name this Revolutionary War battle in which George Washington surprised the Hessians.",
      "answer": "Battle of Trenton"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was demoted after he took the advice of the spy Yoshira and refused to attack. In a strait near Jindo Island, this man’s dozen ships fended off Todo Takatora’s much larger fleet. This man was killed by a stray arquebus bullet in the Battle of Noryang, during the later stages of the Imjin War. This admiral lost no ships in the Battle of Myeongnyang. Turtle ships defended the Joseon kingdom against Toyotomi Hideyoshi under, for ten points, what 16th century Korean naval commander?",
      "answer": "Yi Sun-sin"
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. In 1993, one of these events was organized by Susan Sontag under candlelight only. The documentary The Impossible Itself is about two of these events, held at Luttringhausen and San Quentin prisons. One of these events prominently featured a tree designed by Alberto Giacometti, and the first of these events was witnessed by less than one hundred people in a Paris theater in 1953. For ten points, identify these events in which an absurdist work of Samuel Beckett is shown.",
      "answer": [
        "Productions of Waiting for Godot",
        "synonyms for production, such as staging",
        "performance"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This country ceded the southern part of Dobruja to its southern neighbor in the Treaty of Craiova. Another region of this country, Szekely [see-kay] Land, has a large Hungarian-speaking population. A revolution in this country started in Timisoara [tim-ee-shor-uh] in 1989, and it traces its modern history to the 1859 unification of the principalities of Wallachia and Moldavia. This country is separated from Transylvania by the Carpathian Mountains. Vlad the Impaler once lived in, for ten points, what country with capital Bucharest?",
      "answer": "Romania"
    },
    {
      "question": "After waiting over 800 days to be confirmed as U.S. Ambassador to this country, Cassandra Butts died of leukemia in 2016. The Hawksbill Creek Agreement guarantees that a planned city in this country enjoys no taxation; that city of Freeport on this country’s “Grand” island is now a prominent tourist hub. During the Civil War, blockade runners left from Charleston to this country’s port of Nassau. For ten points, name this member of the British Commonwealth, an island chain just east of Florida and northeast of Cuba.",
      "answer": "Commonwealth of The Bahamas"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler executed Helvidius Priscus for defending the Senate’s right to manage state finances. This ruler’s bid for power was supported by Mucianus, the governor of Syria. This ruler worked with Agricola in the pacification of Britain, and he became the patron of historian Josephus, who he met while suppressing the Great Jewish Revolt. Shortly after the death of Nero, this man succeeded Vitellius to end the Year of the Four Emperors. For ten points, name this father of Titus and founder of the Flavian dynasty.",
      "answer": "Vespasian or Titus Flavius Vespasianus"
    },
    {
      "question": "An event that took place at this location filled the North Fork of the Toutle River with sediment and destroyed the tourist camps at Spirit Lake. At this location, known to the Klickitat tribe as Louwala-Clough, photographer Reid Blackburn was killed near Coldwater Camp; in the aftermath of that event, Jimmy Carter described this location’s surroundings as more desolate than a moonscape. For ten points, name this mountain in the Cascades that killed 57 people in a May 18, 1980 volcanic eruption.",
      "answer": "Mount St. Helens"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man resisted his initial calling, saying that he was too young to speak; when he did begin his ministry, the people of his hometown tried to kill him, for which God promised destruction on the town of Anathoth. Near the end of his life, this man was forcibly taken to Egypt with his scribe Baruch, who recorded this man’s sayings into a namesake book. For ten points, name this Israelite, often called the “weeping prophet,” the author of the Book of Lamentations.",
      "answer": "Jeremiah"
    },
    {
      "question": "An introductory quote made by this man titles a book chronicling his activities, I Heard You Paint Houses. This man rose to power by organizing support for Dave Beck. A prison sentence that this man received for illegally distributing pension funds was commuted by Richard Nixon in 1971. After eating at the Machus Red Fox restaurant outside of Detroit, this man vanished mysteriously in 1975. For ten points, name this thirteen-year president of the International Brotherhood of Teamsters.",
      "answer": "James “Jimmy” Hoffa"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 2010, this city’s Park Kultury metro stop was suicide-bombed by two women working for Doku Umarov. Special forces were criticized for indiscriminately killing 130 civilians with poison gas while trying to resolve a hostage crisis in a theatre in this city. In 1999, FSB agents were accused of staging false flag apartment bombings upon this capital city in order to justify the Second Chechen War. For ten points, name this capital of the Russian Federation.",
      "answer": "Moscow"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This composer dedicated his song “The Little Brook” to Joseph Goebbels and wrote an Olympic Hymn that premiered at the 1936 Berlin Olympics. This composer used both a D clarinet and the French horn to represent the title trickster in his tone poem Till Eulenspeigel’s Merry Pranks. A C-G-C motif opens the “Sunrise” section of another tone poem by this composer, based on a book by Friedrich Nietzsche [nee-cha]. For ten points, name this composer of Also Sprach Zarathustra.",
        "answer": "Richard Strauss"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Richard Strauss also wrote this opera, based on an Oscar Wilde play, in which the title daughter of Herod performs the “Dance of the Seven Veils.”",
        "answer": "Salome"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s forces blundered by shooting Hayward Shepherd in the view of train passengers, who then alerted authorities. An earlier group led by this man attempted to kill Dutch Henry in the Pottawatomie Massacre during Bleeding Kansas. The Battle Hymn of the Republic was set to the tune of a song about the body of this man, who was hanged for attacking a federal armory. For ten points, name this radical abolitionist who launched an 1859 raid on Harpers Ferry.",
        "answer": "John Brown"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Battle Hymn of the Republic was written by this poet and activist, who was inspired by the melody of “John Brown’s Body.”",
        "answer": "Julia Ward Howe"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler abandoned his French allies by signing the Treaty of Breslau, exiting a conflict he later re-entered by invading Bohemia. This ruler’s father captured him in the act of fleeing to England, then forced him to watch the execution of his lover, Hans van Katte. This ruler connected his territory in the First Partition of Poland, and this builder of Sanssouci [san-soo-see] Palace started the War of the Austrian Succession by invading Silesia. For ten points, name this “Great” king of Prussia.",
        "answer": "Frederick the Great or Frederick II"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Frederick allied himself in the Seven Years War with England against Russia, France, and Austria in this event, a reversal of traditional European alliances.",
        "answer": "Diplomatic Revolution"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country indicted Tatsuya Kato for his reporting of the aftermath of a 2013 disaster that killed 304 people, including numerous students from Danwon High School. Wikileaks released a 2007 diplomatic cable in which this country’s current president was accused of being under the control of a “Rasputin” like figure. Choi Soon-sil faces charges of influencing Park Geun-Hye, the president of, for ten points, what Asian country where protesters against Park flooded the streets of Seoul?",
        "answer": "South Korea or Republic of Korea"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The aforementioned 2013 disaster was the sinking of this ferry, which capsized after a sharp turn off the southwest coast of South Korea.",
        "answer": "MV Sewol"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This leader was beaten despite the actions of the king Prasutagus, who had betrothed his land to Claudius. The Ninth Legion was destroyed by this leader’s forces, along with the allied Trinovantes people. While Suetonius was away campaigning, this leader started a revolt by attacking the colony at Camulodunum. This leader’s defeat at the Battle of Watling Street came after her sack of Londinium. For ten points, name this queen who launched a major revolt in Roman Britain.",
        "answer": "Boudica or Boadicea"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Boudica and Prasutagus were rulers of this tribe in eastern Britain, near modern Suffolk.",
        "answer": "Iceni or Eceni"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Description acceptable. In 2010, Ronnie Lee Gardner opted to undergo this action in accordance with his “Mormon heritage.” Eddie Adams captured a photograph of this action about to be performed against Nguyen Van Lem, a Communist assassin, in 1968 in the streets of Saigon by a police general. When this action is done by a group of people, some may be randomly given blanks to diffuse the personal responsibility. For ten points, name this violent act of punishment often performed by a firing squad.",
        "answer": [
          "shooting the condemned",
          "descriptions of killing someone with a gun, including elaborations mentioning any specific bodily target",
          "equivalents for killing, like execution",
          "any specifically named firearm for gun"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A famous photograph of an Execution of a German Communist in Munich appears to be staged, as most of the Freikorps firing squad is ill-prepared to fire. The photo was taken in January 1919 during this general strike in post-World War I Germany, which ended with the executions of Rosa Luxemburg and Karl Liebknecht.",
        "answer": "Spartacist Uprising Revolt, Rebellion, War, etc."
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This singer collaborated with Stevie Wonder on “Ebony and Ivory” and with Michael Jackson on 1983’s “Say Say Say.” In 1984, this man convinced Michael Jackson of the benefit of owning copyrights to songs; Jackson promptly outbid this man for his own catalog of songs. In January 2017, this man sued Sony Music Publishing in another attempt to gain ownership of “The Long and Winding Road” and “Yesterday,” songs on which he shares a writing credit with John Lennon. For ten points, name this bass guitarist for the Beatles.",
        "answer": "James Paul McCartney"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "To avoid losing millions of pounds to tax, McCartney and the other Beatles founded this corporation, which published new Beatles material starting in 1968. Allen Klein’s brief leadership of this company is often cited as a contributing factor for the band’s breakup.",
        "answer": [
          "Apple Corps, Inc.",
          "Apple Publishing and/or Apple Records"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A political cartoon of this man depicts him urging his soldiers to fight while sitting on the mast of a boat with a telescope. This man rose to fame after a victory against Robert Garnett at Rich Mountain. He ran on a ticket with George Pendleton, though the capture of Atlanta hurt his peace platform in a presidential campaign. This man was removed from command after failing to pursue Robert E. Lee’s troops after a victory at Antietam. For ten points, name this overly-cautious Union general who ran against Lincoln in the 1864 election.",
        "answer": "George McClellan"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the Peninsular Campaign in summer 1862, McClellan’s indecision led to his failure to capture Richmond in this set of battles, including skirmishes at Oak Grove and Malvern Hill.",
        "answer": [
          "Seven Days Battles",
          "equivalents"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Plessy v. Ferguson",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "State in which Plessy was arrested for occupying a whites-only railcar in New Orleans.",
          "answer": "Louisiana"
        },
        {
          "question": "Three-word phrase for the Plessy-approved form of segregation.",
          "answer": "separate but equal"
        },
        {
          "question": "1954 case that overturned Plessy.",
          "answer": "Brown v. Board of Education of Topeka, Kansas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Civil rights activist who repeated Plessy’s crime on a Montgomery bus on December 1, 1955.",
          "answer": "Rosa Parks"
        },
        {
          "question": "Law clerk who wrote a “Random Thought” supporting Plessy in 1952 and later became Chief Justice.",
          "answer": "William Rehnquist"
        },
        {
          "question": "Only Justice who dissented in Plessy.",
          "answer": "John Marshall Harlan I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Clause of the 14th Amendment, immediately following the Due Process clause, interpreted in Plessy.",
          "answer": [
            "Equal Protection Clause",
            "descriptive answers that use forms of those two words"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Judge and lawyer who argued for Plessy before the Supreme Court and coined the legal term “color blind.”",
          "answer": "Albion Tourg´ee"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Bubonic Plague",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Color used to describe the Bubonic Plague’s “death.”",
          "answer": [
            "black",
            "the Black Death"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Flea-laden rodents that spread the plague by stowing away in ships.",
          "answer": "rats"
        },
        {
          "question": "People that helped spread the disease while conquering the largest contiguous empire in history.",
          "answer": "Mongols"
        },
        {
          "question": "Political system between lords and vassals that declined in part due to the plague.",
          "answer": [
            "feudalism or manorialism",
            "word forms"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Italian island where the plague first reached Europe in the port of Messina.",
          "answer": "Sicily"
        },
        {
          "question": "Scientific name of the plague-causing bacteria.",
          "answer": "yersinia pestis or Y. pestis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Crimean port city where the plague entered Europe in 1347, via flung corpses.",
          "answer": [
            "Caffa",
            "Feodosia",
            "Theodosia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Ruler and son of Oz Beg who ordered the corpses flung into that Crimean city.",
          "answer": "Jani Beg Khan"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Nobel Peace Prize Winners",
      "prompt": "Given the year of the award and a clue, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "1993: Former South African prisoner who was a co-recipient with F.W. de Klerk.",
          "answer": "Nelson Mandela"
        },
        {
          "question": "2014: Pakistani teenage activist for education of girls.",
          "answer": [
            "Malala Yousafzai",
            "either"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "2001: Global diplomatic organization then led by co-winner, Secretary General Kofi Annan.",
          "answer": "United Nations"
        },
        {
          "question": "1991: Burmese democratic activist, under house arrest at the time of the award.",
          "answer": "Aung San Suu Kyi"
        },
        {
          "question": "2011: Liberian President and women’s rights activist.",
          "answer": "Ellen Johnson Sirleaf"
        },
        {
          "question": "1901: organization founded by one of the first winners, Henry Dunant.",
          "answer": "International Committee of the Red Cross"
        },
        {
          "question": "2015: Country where a National Dialogue Quartet worked for democratic change after the Jasmine Revolution.",
          "answer": [
            "Tunisia",
            "Tunisian National Dialogue Quartet"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "2010: Chinese activist and supporter of Charter 08, who remains a political prisoner.",
          "answer": "Liu Xiaobo"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader’s Anti-Radical Decree prevented communists from taking jobs as teachers. In the midst of negotiating the boundaries of the Oder-Neisse line with Poland, this leader performed the kniefall [”kneefall”] in front of a (20 pts)",
        "monument to victims of the Warsaw Ghetto Uprising. This Social Democrat was forced to resign when his aide, Gunter Guillaume [ghee-ohm], was revealed to be a (10 pts)",
        "Stasi agent from a neighboring country. For ten points, name this West German chancellor who won the 1971 Nobel Peace Prize for his practice of ostpolitik."
      ],
      "answer": "Willy Brandt"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This scientist worked with Pierre-Simon Laplace on a work read to the Royal Academy of Sciences, Memoir on Heat. He discovered that respiration is a form of combustion and that diamonds are composed of carbon. Works by this chemist include his (20 pts)",
        "Essays Physical and Chemical and his Elementary Treatise on Chemistry. This chemist named oxygen and hydrogen and disproved the phlogiston theory; he also developed the law of conservation of mass before (10 pts)",
        "losing his head to the guillotine. For ten points, name this French scientist, often considered the father of modern chemistry."
      ],
      "answer": "Antoine Lavoisier"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One of this artist’s works was inspired by the Zong massacre. This artist requested that he be buried in the canvas of his work showing the title character across from the tomb of Sychaeus [sih-KAY-us]. This “painter of light” and artist of (20 pts)",
        "Dido Building Carthage obscured Hannibal’s army in one of two works titled Snow-Storm. In the 1840s, he painted the (10 pts)",
        "Maidenhead Railway Bridge with a train barreling toward the viewer. For ten points, name this painter of Slave Ship and Rain, Steam, and Speed."
      ],
      "answer": "Joseph Mallord William Turner"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A woman who married into this family was indigo developer Eliza Lucas. A member of this family was the unsuccessful running mate of John Adams in the election of 1800, and earlier shouted “No, no, not a sixpence!” during the XYZ Affair alongside John Marshall and (20 pts)",
        "Elbridge Gerry. Another member of this family negotiated a very popular treaty guaranteeing the U.S. navigational rights on the Mississippi River; that 1791 treaty was with (10 pts)",
        "Spain. Charles Cotesworth and Thomas were part of, for ten points, what prominent early South Carolina family?"
      ],
      "answer": "Pinckney"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The court of this king resolved a disputation in which Nicholas Donin pressed charges of blasphemy against the Talmud. This king allowed Henry III to keep his conquests in Aquitaine despite defeating him at (20 pts)",
        "Taillebourg. During a campaign, this king was captured by the troops of Baibars and Qutuz. Damietta was given to the Mamluks in exchange for the release of this king following the Battle of Al-Mansurah. This king died of dysentery in modern-day (10 pts)",
        "Tunisia while leading the Eighth Crusade. For ten points, name this only French monarch to be canonized."
      ],
      "answer": "Louis IX or Saint Louis"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One philosopher at this school criticized the collectivist foundations of a colleague’s work in his Liberalism and the Limits of Justice. That philosopher, Michael Sandel, teaches a popular introductory course on “Justice” at this university. Another philosopher affiliated with this university allowed for large inequalities if they were a result of free exchange in his (20 pts)",
        "Anarchy, State, and Utopia; that philosopher was Robert Nozick. Both of those works were written in response to another author from this university, who developed the idea of the (10 pts)",
        "“veil of ignorance” in his A Theory of Justice. For ten points, name this Ivy League school where John Rawls taught."
      ],
      "answer": "Harvard University"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The cameraman Max Stahl helped expose troops from this country who had fired on protesters at a cemetery in Santa Cruz. This country initiated the Konfrontasi standoff to prevent an amalgamation of neighboring states to its west. (20 pts)",
        "Mohammed Hatta helped this country secure its independence from the Netherlands in 1949. The principles of pancasila inspired this country’s (10 pts)",
        "“New Order,” which replaced the idea of “Guided Democracy.” For ten points, name this Southeast Asian country whose president Suharto invaded East Timor."
      ],
      "answer": "Indonesia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man consolidated power in one union by forcing rivals to listen to peer abuse in a process known as “the Game.” In an attempt to drum up support from Filipinos, this man made the mistake of meeting with Ferdinand Marcos, leading to a break with (20 pts)",
        "Philip Vera Cruz. This man utilized the motto “Si, se puede” [see, say pway-day] during a hunger strike and joined the Delano (10 pts)",
        "grape march on Sacramento to fight for higher wages for laborers. For ten points, name this Mexican-American activist who helped found the United Farm Workers."
      ],
      "answer": "C´esar Ch´avez"
    }
  ]
}